Guide to the Brooklyn, N.Y., Department of Law, Corporation Counsel records 2013.015
Brooklyn Historical Society
Brooklyn, N.Y., Department of Law, Corporation Counsel records
Bulk, 1894-1905
1843-1920
2013.015
Brooklyn Historical Society
118.0 linear feet in 235 manuscript boxes, 4 flat boxes, 1 flat file drawer, and 1 oversize shelf
The collection consists of the records of the office of the Corporation Counsel of the City of Brooklyn and, following the 1898 consolidation of the Greater City of New York, the records of the Brooklyn office of the Corporation Counsel of the City of New York. The bulk of the collection comprises legal documents related to complaints filed against the city. The Corporation Counsel was also responsible for overseeing the opening of city streets and the collection includes a series of records related to these matters. On the whole, the collection documents the activities of the Brooklyn Corporation Counsel, as well as the day-to-day legal issues that the citizens of Brooklyn faced in the 19th and early 20th centuries. It also documents the rapid expansion of Brooklyn’s infrastructure, especially its streets and water supply. The Brooklyn, N.Y., Department of Law, Corporation Counsel records collection spans the years 1843 to 1920 (bulk dates 1894 to 1905).
Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.). Department of Law.
New York (N.Y.). Law Department.
Related Archival Materials note
The Brooklyn Historical Society holds several collections related to the Corporation Counsel records, including:
Brooklyn 26th Ward improvement report for New Jersey Avenue, 1891 (1987.008)
Brooklyn City Court records, 1893-1905 (1977.332)
Brooklyn Fourth Ward tax assessment book and scrapbook, circa 1840-1900 (1978.128)
Brooklyn, N.Y., Bureau of Sewers records, circa 1853-1988 (ARC.235)
Brooklyn Roads collection, 1825-1883 (1977.337)
Brooklyn tax document collection, 1864-1909 (1986.012)
Brooklyn Treasurer and City Court Clerk receipt books, 1827-1869 (1985.089)
City of Brooklyn Collector of Gas Lamp Tax Assessment ledgers, 1855-1856 (1986.010)
City of Brooklyn property tax assessments, 1841 (1978.158)
Fulton Street assessment agreement, 1841 (1978.041)
Joseph Arthur Burr, Jr. composition book, 1860-1866 (1973.108)
Myrtle Street assessment petition, 1834-1834 (1978.040)
Queens County Treasurer’s Office land auction receipts, 1892-1897 (1977.572)
Roll of assessment for the grading and paving of Flatbush Avenue, April 17, 1857 (1973.089)
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The source of this collection is unknown. The collection was accessioned in 2013.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to researchers without restriction, with the exception of two files related to adoptions.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of the records of the office of the Corporation Counsel of the City of Brooklyn and, following the 1898 consolidation of the Greater City of New York, the records of the Brooklyn office of the Corporation Counsel of the City of New York. The collection spans the years 1843 to 1920 (bulk dates 1850 to 1905) and measures 113 linear feet. The bulk of the collection comprises legal documents related to complaints filed against the city. Common complaints include personal injury claims, property damage claims (mostly related to the city’s sewer system), assessment disputes, and civil service grievances. The Corporation Counsel was also responsible for overseeing the opening of city streets and the collection includes a series of records related to this activity. The collection also includes correspondence with various city departments (Water Supply, Finance, Police, etc.) that sought legal advice.
While the majority of the collection is Brooklyn specific, portions of the collection deal with other nearby areas, especially Queens County and Long Island. Specifically, from 1896 to 1899, there are several complaints related to Long Island City. There are also a number of files related to property acquired by the City of Brooklyn (and later the City of New York) in the Towns of Jamaica and Hempstead on Long Island relating to the expansion of the city’s water supply.
On the whole, the collection documents the activities of the Brooklyn Corporation Counsel as well as the day-to-day legal issues that the citizens of Brooklyn faced in the 19th and early 20th centuries. It also documents the rapid expansion of Brooklyn’s infrastructure, especially its streets and water supply.
Biographical/Historical note
The charter for the City of Brooklyn that consolidated the Village of Brooklyn with the Town of Brooklyn was approved in 1834. The charter established the city’s municipal government which consisted of a mayor and a common council. The common council was granted the power to appoint various positions, including a separate Attorney and Counsel. These positions were typically occupied by a single appointee, except from 1847 to 1850 when they were held by two separate appointees. The 1873 charter of the City of Brooklyn established a single Attorney and Counsel as head of the city’s Law Department. The charter specified that the Attorney and Counsel would serve as chief legal advisor for the mayor, the common council, and the various city departments established over the years. The Attorney and Counsel was also charged with managing the proceedings necessary for opening, closing, or otherwise improving city streets. By 1885, the position title was changed from Attorney and Counsel to Corporation Counsel. In 1898, the City of Brooklyn was consolidated into the Greater City of New York. The Brooklyn office of the Corporation Counsel subsequently reported to the Corporation Counsel of the City of New York and was headed by an Assistant Corporation Counsel. The Brooklyn office handled all legal matters that affected the Borough of Brooklyn and Kings County.
Arrangement note
The collection is organized in the following series:
Series 1: Case Files, 1849-1920
Series 2: Streets, 1844-1912
Series 3: Correspondence, 1866-1913
Series 4: Property Files, 1851-1918
Series 5: Laws, 1867-1898
Series 6: Miscellaneous, 1843-1915
Other Finding Aids note
Files relating to specific locations have been mapped and can be browsed visually at: http://brooklynhistory.org/library/wp/brooklyn-corporation-counsel-records-1843-1920/
Adams, John P., 1839?-1895; Atlantic Avenue Railroad Company.; Bell, James D., 1845-1919; Broadway Ferry and Metropolitan Railroad Company.; Brooklyn and Jamaica Bay Turnpike Company.; Brooklyn and Jamaica Plank Road Company.; Brooklyn and Rockaway Beach Railroad Company.; Brooklyn Borough Gas Company.; Brooklyn Central Railway Company.; Brooklyn City and Newtown Railroad Company.; Brooklyn City Railroad Co. (New York, N.Y.).; Brooklyn Elevated Railroad Company.; Brooklyn Heights Railroad Company.; Brooklyn Institute of Arts and Sciences.; Brooklyn Queens County and Suburban Railroad Company.; Brooklyn Rapid Transit Company.; Brooklyn Steam Transit Company.; Brooklyn Traction Company.; Brooklyn Union Gas Company.; Brooklyn Wharf and Warehouse Company.; Brower, George V., 1842-1921; Burr, J. Arthur, (Joseph Arthur); Carr, William J., 1862-1917; Chittenden, R. Percy, 1866-; Church of the Redeemer (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.).; Citizens Electric Illuminating Company of Brooklyn.; Coler, Bird Sim, 1867-1941; Coney Island and Brooklyn Railroad Company.; Coney Island Fuel Gas and Light Company.; Coney Island Jockey Club.; Dalton, William; DeKalb Avenue Railroad Company.; DeWitt, William C.; East River and Atlantic Ocean Railroad Company.; Edison Electric Illuminating Company of Brooklyn.; Electric Illuminating and Power Company of Long Island City.; Ellison, William B.; Equity Gas Light Company of the Eastern District.; Feitner, Thomas L., 1847-1929; Flatbush Gas Company.; Fulton Elevated Railroad Company.; Green-Wood Cemetery (New York, N.Y.).; Greenwood, Richard B.; Grout, Edward M., 1861-; Jamaica Electric Light Company.; Jenks, Almet Francis, 1853-1924; Kane, James; Kearney, Henry S.; Keating, James P., 1849?-1919; Kings County Elevated Railroad Company (New York, N.Y.).; Kings County Gas and Illuminating Company.; Kings County Water Supply Company.; Long Island Railroad Company.; Long Island Water Supply Company.; Manhattan Railway Company.; McDonald, Albert G.; Merrick Water Company.; Moffett, James; Mudge, Alfred E.; Municipal Electric Light Company of Brooklyn.; Nassau Electric Railroad Company.; New York (N.Y.). Board of Assessors.; New York and New Jersey Telephone Company.; New York and Queens County Railway Company.; New York and Sea Beach Railway Company.; New York Elevated Railroad Company.; New York, Brooklyn and Manhattan Beach Railway Company.; North Second Street and Middle Village Railroad Company.; Ocean Electric Railway Company.; Rives, George Lockhart, 1849-1917; Scannell, John J., 1841-1918; Sea Beach Railway Company.; Seaside and Brooklyn Bridge Elevated Railroad Company.; Simis, Adolph, Jr.; South Brooklyn Railroad and Terminal Company.; Stapleton, Luke D., 1869-1923; Staten Island Electric Railroad Company.; Swanstrom, J. Edward, 1853-; Taylor, John A., 1844-; Title Guarantee and Trust Company (New York, N.Y.).; Union Elevated Railroad Company.; Union Ferry Company (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.).; Union Gas Light Company.; Watson, Archibald R.; Whalen, John, 1854-1926; White, Alfred Tredway, 1846-1921; Whitney, D. D., Jr.; Williamsburg Gas Company.; Acquisition of property |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Acquisition of property |z New York (State) |z Nassau County; Actions and defenses |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Athletic clubs |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Bay Ridge (New York, N.Y); Bedford-Stuyvesant (New York, N.Y.); Black-and-white prints (photographs); Blueprints (reprographic copies); Boerum Hill (New York, N.Y.); Bonds (legal records); Borough Park (New York, N.Y.); Breweries |z New York (State) |z New York; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn Bridge (New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn Heights (New York, N.Y.); Brownsville (New York, N.Y.); Bushwick (New York, N.Y.); Business cards; Canarsie (New York, N.Y.); Carroll Gardens (New York, N.Y.); City attorneys |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Civil Service |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Clinton Hill (New York, N.Y.); Cobble Hill (New York, N.Y.); Coney Island (New York, N.Y.); Contracts; Correspondence; Court records |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Courts |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Crown Heights (New York, N.Y.); Cypress Hills (New York, N.Y.); Deeds; Downtown Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); DUMBO (New York, N.Y.); East New York (New York, N.Y.); East River (N.Y.); Elections |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Flatbush (New York, N.Y.); Flatlands (New York, N.Y.); Fort Greene (New York, N.Y.); Gowanus (New York, N.Y.); Gowanus Canal (New York, N.Y.); Gravesend (New York, N.Y.); Greenpoint (New York, N.Y.); Hempstead (N.Y.); Jamaica (New York, N.Y.); Jamaica Bay (N.Y.); Judicial records; Kings County (N.Y.); Leases; Legal documents; Legislative acts; Licenses; Local elections |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Long Island City (New York, N.Y.); Maps; Midwood (New York, N.Y.); Mortgages; Municipal government |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Nassau County (N.Y.); Navy-yards and naval stations |z New York (State) |z Kings County; New Utrecht (New York, N.Y.); Newtown Creek (Kings County-New York County, N.Y.); Notes; Park Slope (New York, N.Y.); Payroll records; Photographs; Prospect Heights (New York, N.Y.); Prospect Lefferts Gardens (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Prospect Park (New York, N.Y.); Public records; Queens (New York, N.Y.); Queens County (N.Y.); Railroads |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Railroads, Elevated |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Real property |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Real property |z New York (State) |z Long Island; Real property |z New York (State) |z Queens County; Red Hook (New York, N.Y.); Roads |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Sheepshead Bay (New York, N.Y.); Staten Island (New York, N.Y.); Streets |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Summonses; Sunset Park (New York, N.Y.); Tax assessment |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Tax records; Taxation |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Wages |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Wages |z New York (State) |z New York; Water rights |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Water-supply |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Waterfronts |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Williamsburg (New York, N.Y.); Wills; Windsor Terrace (New York, N.Y.)
- Series 1: Case Files, 1849-1920; 98.0 linear feet; in 199 manuscripts boxes, 4 flat boxes and 1 flat file drawer
  Arrangement note
  The series is arranged chronologically by year and then alphabetically by folder title. Records that relate to the same case have been grouped together by the processing archivist into individual folders.
  Folder titles are formatted as follows:
  Individual (Surname, Forename) or Corporate Name – Description of the case
  Example: Samuels, Esther - Hudson Ave. sidewalk injury
  The location with respect to the case is included in the folder title if known.
  Please see the Processing Information note for additional general information regarding the arrangement of the series in this collection.
  Scope and Contents
  This series is comprised of case files documenting legal complaints filed against the City of Brooklyn (and after 1897, the City of New York) for a variety of matters including personal injuries, property damage, compensation for goods and services, civil service disputes, and assessment and tax disputes. The series also includes a smaller number of complaints filed by the city against individuals and corporations for legal violations or property foreclosures.
  The records span the years 1849 to 1920 (bulk dates 1894 to 1905).
  The files were compiled by the office of the Corporation Counsel and contain legal documents including, but not limited to, affidavits, briefs, complaints, examination transcripts, and various notices. The files may include related correspondence, legal notes, and other supporting documents.
  The majority of the personal injury cases involve injuries that occurred on city streets and sidewalks although a smaller number involve other city property such as parks and bridges (including the Brooklyn Bridge). Some cases name local railroad companies as co-defendants. The files sometimes include reports from police and/or doctors.
  Property damage claims primarily relate to overflowing sewers. Neighborhoods that were especially prone to flooding include Bedford-Stuyvesant, Bushwick, Williamsburg, Greenpoint, Fort Greene, and Boerum Hill/Gowanus. These files sometimes include lists of household or commercial goods and their values. The series includes some claims for property damage in areas outside of Brooklyn, especially the Town of Hempstead on Long Island, for damage related to Brooklyn’s water supply such as flooding from pumping stations and the diversion of creeks and other waterways.
  There are a number of claims for unpaid goods and services provided to the city. These complaints are sometimes related to contract disputes between the plaintiffs, the city and other contractors. Claims related to construction or alterations of city buildings (such as schools and police stations) sometimes include specifications for the work.
  The series also includes disputes related to civil service employment, typically dismissals or claims for unpaid salaries.
  Another large component of the series comprises complaints related to assessments and other property matters. These files may include documents providing details about property ownership such as deeds and property searches. A small number of complaints include property maps.
  Other matters addressed in the series include railroad company disputes, gas and electric utility disputes, election disputes, license disputes (especially liquor licenses and licenses to hold athletic contests), building and health violations, county jail discharges, estate disputes, and a small number of criminal matters.
  While the majority of the series is Brooklyn specific, from 1896 to 1899, there are a number of complaints relating to Long Island City that concern assessments, civil service, or claims for goods and services.
  The legal repercussions of the consolidation of the Greater City of New York are also evident in the series. Civil service complaints about disparate pay for similar positions in the former municipal governments resulted in litigation. Also of note is a dispute arising from the debt apportionment of Queens County.
  Additionally, this series includes a small number of complaints arising from other areas of New York City, such as Manhattan and Staten Island.
  - Spooner, Edwin B. against Samuel B. Hicks, 1849 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Cromwell, Charles G., 1852 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Dunn, Michael, Bartlett Sweeny, and Patrick Mooney, 1852-1853 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Cromwell, Charles T. against Lindsay J. Well and Stephen B. Story, 1853 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    General note
    Court St. and Church St. (now West 9th St.)
  - Health and Building Violations (Various), 1854- 1956 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Kalbfleisch, Martin - Opening Grand St., from Bushwick Ave. to Metropolitan Ave., 1858 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Lomas, John - DeKalb Ave. Sewer Property Damage, 1859 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Reed, G. Fred - Willet and Son contract dispute, 1859 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Includes masonry specifications
  - Hill, Simon - North 3rd St. and 3rd St. - Lot 2329/1601 assessment, circa 1860s (Box 1, Folder 9)
    3rd St. is now known as Berry St.
  - Union Ferry Company - Fulton St. encroachment, 1860 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Litchfield, E. B. - Assessments, circa 1861 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Ward 6 - Block 27 - Lots 4-11 (Congress St., between Clinton St. and Henry St.)
  - Chapman, George M. - Assessment, 1862-1869 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Lafayette Ave., from Bedford Ave. to Division Ave. (now Broadway)
  - Roets, John R. and Richard B. Kimball, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Rufus Gardner summons
  - Nicholson Pavement Company, 1868 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Lowery, Charles J. - Asessment dispute, circa 1870 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Williamsburg Gas Company - Encroachment upon the waters of the foot of North 11th St., circa 1870 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Baldwin, Thomas - Hemstead Reservoir property award, 1871 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Coit, William A. - Vacate assessment, 1871 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Atlantic St., from Henry St. to Flatbush Ave.
  - Daniels, DeWitt C., Edward Root, and Charles C. Foster against the City of Brooklyn - Construction dispute, 1871 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    Building on 10th St. (north side), between 4th Ave. and 5th Ave.
  - Dennis, Charles and others - Assessment petition, 1871-1872 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    Repaving Montague St., from Pierrepont Pl. to Court St.
  - Eature (?), James and others, 1871 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Ford, Nathaniel - Vacate assessment, 1871 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    Improving Union St., from Columbia St. to Gowanus Canal
  - Jones, D. S. - Petition against resolution to fence lots on 5th Ave., from 19th St. to 20th St., 1871 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Markey, Francis - Assessment dispute, 1871 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    Repaving Main St., from Prospect St. to the River
  - Wheeler, Andrew S. - Pacific St. and Washington Ave. foreclosure, 1871-1876 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Amory, Peter B. - Assessment reduction, 1872 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    Myrtle Ave., from Broadway to City line opening
  - Bliss, William - Hose couplings patents, 1872 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Hempstead Gas Light Company and others - Damage to Hempstead Reservoir water supply, 1872-1874 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Marsh, James, Jr. against Board of Health, 1872 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Meeker, Samuel M., 1872-1873 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Richard, George - Assessment dispute, 1872-1873 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    Scholes St. - Lots 1609 and 1666
  - Stevens, Calvin, 1872 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Swift, Francis - Foreclosure, 1872-1873 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    Grand St. (now part of Borinquen Pl.), between 9th St. (now Rodney St.) and 10th St. (now Keap St.)
  - Woodruff, Albert C. (Long Island Club) - Claim to Surplus Money, 1872 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Burrows, Lemuel - Tax collector theft, 1873 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Derlin, Felix, 1873 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Fitzgerald, John - 1st St. paving contract, circa 1873 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Kessler, Rudolph (clerk) - Theft of Bonds, 1873-1874 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Lowery, Charles J. against Andrew S. Wheeler and the City of Brooklyn - Foreclosure, 1873 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    Block bound by 1st St. (Kent Ave.), North 5th St., North 6th St., and East River
  - Munn, Arson D. - Assessment dispute, 1873-1875 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    Ward 22 (all): Block 29 - Lots 38-40, 42, 48-50; Block 116 - Lot 18; Block 117 - Lot 71; Block 119 - Lots 1, 1a, 4-5; Block 120 - Lot 6; Area around 4th Ave., Sackett St., President St., and Powers St; and property bound by 8th Ave., 9th Ave., Union St., and President St.; Includes property maps
  - Seccomb, Edward A. against Cortland A. Sprague and others - 126 Willow St. foreclosure, 1873 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    Formerly 128 Willow St.
  - Sorchan, Marius A. - Vacate assessment, 1873 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    Improvement of Atlantic Ave., from Classon Ave. to east City line
  - White, Robert W. - 5th Ave. sewer accident, 1873 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Wilson, Charles against Water and Sewerage Commissioners, 1873 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Blake, Peter - Street cleaning services, 1874-1875 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Brennan, Francis, Adam Hill, and Edward McDonald - Contract dispute, 1874-1876 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Cooper, James T. - Gatekeeper salary, 1874 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Doe, John and others - Fulton Ave. paving dispute, 1874 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Johnson, Mary E. - Assessment dispute, 1874 (Box 1, Folder 49)
    Repaving 6th Ave., from Flatbush Ave. to Union St.
  - Kouvalinka, John - Assessment dispute, 1874 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - North Second Street and Middle Village Railroad Company - Property dispute, 1874 (Box 1, Folder 51)
    1st St. (now Kent Ave.), south of Broadway
  - Home Life Insurance Company against Isaac Badeu and others - Foreclosure, 1875-1876 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Property on Brooklyn Ave., between by Fulton Ave. and Herkimer St.
  - Litchfield, Grace - Vacate assessment, 1875 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    7th Ave., from Union St. and 12th St. repairs
  - Ackerly, Samuel, 1876 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - DeKalb Avenue Railroad Company - Repair line from Fulton St. to Broadway, 1876 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Goetz, Wolfging - DeKalb Ave. (north side), near Nostrand Ave. - Water pipe property damage, 1876 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Hartman, Charles - Vacate assessment, 1876 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Ross, William D., 1876 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Building and Fire Escape violations, 1878-1881 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Johnson's Elevated Railroad, Company - Trial of tubular girder, 1878 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Andrews, John - Vacate assessment, 1879 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    20th St., from 6th Ave. to 8th Ave.
  - Brooklyn Steam Transit Company, 1879 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Church of the Pilgrim Chapel - Buidling encroachment, 1879 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    Henry St. and Degraw St.
  - Furman, George E. and Hugh Carey, 1879 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Kelly, Thomas against the Common Council, 1879 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Long Island Railroad Company - Atlantic Ave., Flatbush Ave., Raymond St., Hanson Pl., and Fort Greene Pl. property petition, 1879 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    Formerly Jamaica and Flatbush Turnpike Rd.
  - McGuerney, John againt Sebastian Phillips - Warrant to Remove Tenant, 1879 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    168 Columbia St.
  - Payne, Elisha - 461 and 463 2nd St. assessment, 1879 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    2nd St. is now known as Wythe Ave.
  - Stryker, Michael - Award for St. Marks Ave. opening, 1879 (Box 2, Folder 18)